I run from the liars to fuel on the fire I know I created myself
I know I can't fight the sad days and bad nights, but I'm in the rest for your whole
You can hurt, Louis don't belong together So you took the love from my arms into the heat
Arms of yours, but I don't need it cure for me
I don't need it, but I don't need it cure for me
I don't like the tension, the misapprehensions about our nature in love
The glory is teaches, I know here's the creatures and knows how to play with the cold
You've got the nerves, but they never show unless they hurt
So you blame that all on my love to move me
I'd like God, but I don't need it cure for me
I don't need it, but I don't need it cure for me
I don't need it, but I don't need it
Please, no cure for me
I don't need it, but I don't need it cure for me